Register of the Joseph Hansen Papers, 1887-1980.
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph Hansen Papers,
1887-1980.
92035
Hansen, Joseph, 1910-1979.
109 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 3 envelopes, 1 phonotape cassette (45.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, minutes, reports, internal bulletins, resolutions, theses, printed matter, sound recording, and photographs, relating to Leon Trotsky, activities of the Socialist Workers Party in the United States, and activities of the Fourth International in Latin America, Western Europe and elsewhere.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research but may not be photocopied.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (127 reels).
Access Points
Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Fourth International.; Communism.; Socialism.; Socialist Workers Party.; Communism--United States.; Communism--Latin America.; Communism--Europe.; Socialism--United States.; Socialism--Latin America.; Socialism--Europe.; United States--Politics and government.; Latin America.; Europe.; Journalists.; Phonotapes.
Biographical Note
1910 June 16 Born, Salt Lake City, Utah
1928-1934 Attended University of Utah part-time
1931 Married Reba Hooper
1934 Joined Communist League of America (predecessor of Socialist Workers Party)
1936-1937 Staff writer, Voice of the Federation (Maritime Federation of the Pacific), and Labor Action
1937-1940 Secretary to Leon Trotsky, Coyoacan, Mexico
1939 Author, Father Coughlin: Fascist Demagogue
1940 Author, Wall Street's War, Not Ours!
1940-1975 Member, National Committee, Socialist Workers Party
1941-1945 Merchant seaman
1944 Author, American Workers Need a Labor Party
1945-1954 Staff writer, The Militant (newspaper of Socialist Workers Party)
1946 Socialist Workers Party candidate for United States Senate, New York
1948 National lecture tour on "The Struggle for Power in Europe" Author, The Socialist Workers Party: What It Is, What It Stands For
1950 Socialist Workers Party candidate for United States Senate, New York
1951 National lecture tour on "America and the World Crisis"
1954 Editor, The Militant
1955-1959 Editor, International Socialist Review (theoretical journal of Socialist Workers Party)
1957 Socialist Workers Party candidate for mayor of Los Angeles National lecture tour on "The Outlook for Socialist Regroupment"
1959-1967 Editor, The Militant
1960 Visit to Cuba Founding member, Fair Play for Cuba Committee Author, Too Many Babies? The Myth of the Population Explosion Author, The Truth about Cuba
1961 Attended Conferencia Latinoamericana por la Soberania Nacional, la Emancipacion Economica y la Paz, Mexico City Author, In Defense of the Cuban Revolution: An Answer to the State Department and Theodore Draper
1961-1962 Four-month tour of Latin America
1962 National lecture tour on "What Makes Latin America Explosive" Visit to Algeria Author, The Theory of the Cuban Revolution Author, Trotskyism and the Cuban Revolution: An Answer to Hoy
1962-1965 Socialist Workers Party representative in Europe, based in Paris
1963 Attended 7th (Reunification) World Congress of Fourth International
1963-1979 Fraternal member, United Secretariat of Fourth International Editor, Intercontinental Press (originally entitled World Outlook; published on behalf of United Secretariat of Fourth International, at first in Paris and later in New York City)
1965 Co-author, Khrushchev's Downfall/New Deepening of the Sino-Soviet Rift?
1966 Editor, Healy "Reconstructs" the Fourth International: Documents and Comments by Participants in a Fiasco
1967 Attended Organizacion Latinoamericana de Solidaridad conference, Havana Co-author, Behind China's "Great Cultural Revolution"
1968 Co-author, Murder in Memphis: Martin Luther King and the Future of the Black Liberation Struggle Co-author, The Nature of the Cuban Revolution: Record of a Controversy, 1960-1963 Co-author, Revolt in France, May-June 1968: A Contemporary Record
1969 Attended 9th World Congress of Fourth International Co-author, Class, Party and State and the Eastern European Revolution Co-author, The Invasion of Czechoslovakia Co-author, Leon Trotsky: The Man and His Work: Reminiscences and Appraisals
1972 Author, The Abern Clique Co-author, Nixon's Moscow and Peking Summits: Their Meaning for Vietnam Co-author, A Revolutionary Strategy for the 70s: Documents of the Socialist Workers Party
1973-1977 Fraternal member, Steering Committee, Leninist-Trotskyist Faction of Fourth International
1974 Attended 10th World Congress of Fourth International Author, The Workers and Farmers Government Co-author, Towards a History of the Fourth International Editor, Marxism vs. Ultraleftism: The Record of Healy's Break with Trotskyism
1975 ff. Target of accusation campaign by Workers Revolutionary Party (Great Britain) and Workers League (U.S.)
1976 Co-author, The Fight against Fascism in the USA: Forty Years of Struggle Described by Participants Co-author, Healy's Big Lie: The Slander Campaign against Joseph Hansen, George Novack, and the Fourth International Co-author, What Is American Fascism? Writings on Father Coughlin, Mayor Frank Hague, and Senator Joseph McCarthy
1978 Author, Dynamics of the Cuban Revolution: The Trotskyist View
1979 January 18 Died, New York City
1979 Author, The Leninist Strategy of Party Building: The Debate on Guerrilla Warfare in Latin America (published posthumously)
1980 Author, James P. Cannon the Internationalist (published posthumously)
1986 Co-author, Cosmetics, Fashions, and the Exploitation of Women (published posthumously)
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1930-1979. (Boxes 1-3)
  Genealogical writings, printed matter, obituaries, condolence letters, memorial meeting addresses, memorabilia, and miscellany, relating to the family, student years, and death of Joseph Hansen. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1913-1980. (Boxes 3-35)
  Correspondence of Joseph Hansen arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Correspondence of Reba Hansen, wife of Joseph Hansen, is interfiled. Nationality or country of residence of correspondents is indicated when other than United States.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1928-1978. (Boxes 35-60)
  Speeches and writings by Joseph Hansen arranged chronologically.
- EDITORIAL FILE, 1924-1979. (Boxes 60-67)
  Speeches and writings by others, with editorial annotations or other handwritten commentary by Joseph Hansen. In many, but not all, cases, annotations reflect planned publication in journals edited by Hansen. Arranged alphabetically by author.
- REBA HANSEN FILE, 1928-1979. (Boxes 67-68)
  Papers of Reba Hansen (1909-1990), wife of Joseph Hansen, business manager of Intercontinental Press, and Socialist Workers Party member, including speeches and writings, and miscellany, arranged by physical form.
- BEATRICE HANSEN FILE, 1945-1969. (Box 68)
  Papers of Beatrice Hansen (1925-1969), sister-in-law of Joseph Hansen, and member of the National Committee of the Socialist Workers Party, including correspondence, speeches and writings, and personal documents, arranged by physical form.
- LEON TROTSKY FILE, 1903-1979. (Boxes 69-70)
  Originals and copies of correspondence and speeches and writings of the Russian revolutionary Leon Trotsky (1879-1940); correspondence, writings, and memoranda of members of his household and other associates; and collected printed matter and copies of government documents relating to him. Arranged by physical form.
- NATALIIA SEDOVA TROTSKAIA FILE, 1940-1963. (Box 70)
  Originals and copies of correspondence and speeches and writings of Nataliia Sedova Trotskaia (1882-1962), wife of Leon Trotsky; and collected printed matter relating to her. Arranged by physical form.
- FOURTH INTERNATIONAL FILE, 1930-1980. (Boxes 71-94)
  Correspondence, writings, internal bulletins, resolutions, statements, reports, memoranda, serial issues, pamphlets, and clippings by or about the Fourth International and other Trotskyist-derived groups. Includes internal and public issuances of the Fourth International, its various national sections, and other Trotskyist groups; correspondence of Fourth International leaders; correspondence of Socialist Workers Party leaders on international topics; internal and public issuances of the Socialist Workers Party on international topics; and material relating to the Fourth International, but generated outside it. Does not include writings or correspondence of Joseph Hansen. Arranged alphabetically by country.
- SOCIALIST WORKERS PARTY FILE, 1929-1979. (Boxes 94-98)
  Correspondence, writings, discussion documents, resolutions, reports, memoranda, minutes, and printed matter, by or about the Socialist Workers Party. Includes correspondence of party leaders on domestic topics; internal and public issuances of the party on domestic topics; and material relating to the party but generated outside it. Does not include writings or correspondence of Joseph Hansen. Arranged by physical form.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1887-1978. (Boxes 98-104)
  Collected pamphlets, serial issues, printed articles, clippings, leaflets, bulletins, newsletters, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by topic.
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1976-1977. (Box 105)
  Large format publications.
- INDEXES. (Boxes 106-109)
  Indexes prepared by Library of Social History prior to present arrangement of collection.
- PHONOTAPE, 1977. (Cassette cabinet)
  Sound recording of speech by Joseph Hansen.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, ca. 1900-1975. (10-A.V)
  Prints of Joseph Hansen, family members, and acquaintances.
- INCREMENT, 1927-1972. (Box 110)
  Pamphlets produced by Hansen and yearbook, received after the bulk of the collection was processed, arranged in two subseries, Biographical File and Speeches and Writings.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1930-1979
  - Death. Obituaries, memorial meeting addresses, and condolence letters and messages, 1979
    - Antilles (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Argentina. Includes letters by Nahuel Moreno (Folder 2)
    - Australia (Folder 3)
    - Austria (Folder 4)
    - Belgium. Includes letters by Fernand Charlier and Ernest Mandel (Folder 5)
    - Bolivia (Folder 6)
    - Botswana (Folder 7)
    - Brazil (Folder 8)
    - Canada. Includes letter by Ross Dowson and memorial meeting transcript (Folder 9)
    - Chile. Letter by Luis Vitale (Folder 10)
    - Colombia (Folder 11)
    - Costa Rica. Includes letter by Fausto Amador (Folder 12)
    - Denmark (Folder 13)
    - Ecuador (Folder 14)
    - France
      - Condolence messages. Includes letters by Pierre Broue, Pierre Frank, Jean-Francois Godchau, Pierre Lambert, and Michel Pablo (Folder 15)
      - Obituaries (Folder 16)
    - Germany (Folder 17)
    - Great Britain. Includes letters or messages by John and Mary Archer, Ken Coates, Tamara Deutscher, Sam Gordon, Alan and Connie Harris, and Louis Sinclair (Folder 18)
    - Greece (Folder 19)
    - Hong Kong (Folder 20)
    - India. Includes letters by Sailen Banerji and Sharad Jhaveri (Folder 21)
    - Iran (Folder 22)
    - Israel (Folder 23)
    - Italy. Includes letter by Livio Maitan (Folder 24)
    - Japan (Folder 25)
    - Lebanon (Folder 26)
    - Mauritius (Folder 27)
    - Mexico. Includes letters by Manuel Aguilar and Esteban Volkov, and memorial meeting addresses by Aguilar and Cristina Rivas (Folder 28)
    - New Zealand (Folder 29)
    - Panama (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Peru. Includes letter by Hugo Blanco (Folder 2)
    - Puerto Rico (Folder 3)
    - Spain (Folder 4)
    - Sri Lanka. Letter by Bala Tampoe (Folder 5)
    - Sweden (Folder 6)
    - Switzerland. Includes letter by George von Steiger (Folder 7)
    - United States
      - Condolence messages to Reba Hansen. Includes letters by Kay Burch, Morris and Pearl Chertov, Max Geldman, Milton and Tybie Genecin, C. Frank and Grace Glass, Conrad D. Hansen, Ellarean Hansen, Asher and Ruth Harer, Clara Kaye, Chris Moustakis, Peng Shu-tse and Ch'en Pi-lan, Della Rossa, Ruth Schein, Ted and Dot Selander, Ann Snipper, Suzanne Weiss, and Tim Wohlforth (Folder 8-10)
      - Condolence messages to Socialist Workers Party. Includes letters or messages by Pearl Chertov, C. Frank and Grace Glass, David McReynolds, Chris Moustakis, and Morris and Sylvia Stein (Folder 11)
      - Memorial meeting addresses
        - New York City. Includes addresses or messages by Jack Barnes, Michael Baumann, Farrell and Marvel Dobbs, and Peng Shu-tse and Ch'en Pi-lan. See also Death/Mexico (Folder 12)
        - San Francisco. Includes address by Ruth Schein (Folder 13)
        - Seattle. Includes addresses by Stephanie Coontz and Richard Garza (Folder 14)
      - Obituaries (Folder 15-16)
    - Uruguay (Folder 17)
    - Venezuela. Includes letter by Alfonso Ramirez (Folder 18)
  - Drawing of Joseph Hansen as a young man by Edwin Herron, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Family
    - DeWolfe, Louise (sister of Joseph Hansen). Notes and letters re legal and medical affairs, 1973 (Folder 2)
    - Hansen, Conrad J. Z. (father of Joseph Hansen). Autobiographical and genealogical writings, 1971-1975 (Folder 3-4)
    - Hansen, Rose (mother of Joseph Hansen). Autobiographical and genealogical writings, 1962-1965 (Folder 5)
    - Miscellany. Letters, clippings, and genealogical writings, 1942-1966 (Folder 6)
  - Miscellany. Memorabilia and bills, 1930-1943 (Folder 7)
  - Publishing fund. Announcements, lists, and statistics, 1979 (Folder 8)
  - University of Utah
    - General. Grades and clippings, 1931-1932 (Folder 9)
    - University Pen (campus literary magazine, of which Joseph Hansen was an editor). Printed copies
      - 1931-1932 (Folder 10)
      - 1933-1935 (Folder 11)
    - Utah Humbug (campus humor magazine, to which Joseph Hansen was a contributor). Printed copies, 1933 (Folder 12)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1913-1980
  - General
    - Algeria, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Argentina
      - 1940-1969 (Folder 14)
      - 1970-1978 (Folder 15)
    - Australia, 1965-1973 (Folder 16)
    - Austria, 1969-1973 (Folder 17)
    - Belgium, 1965-1976 (Folder 18)
    - Bolivia, 1941-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Brazil, 1945-1977 (Folder 2)
    - Canada
      - 1956-1971 (Folder 3)
      - 1972-1977 (Folder 4)
    - Chile, 1945-1973 (Folder 5)
    - Colombia, 1962-1978 (Folder 6)
    - Costa Rica, 1976-1978 (Folder 7)
    - Cuba, 1957-1978 (Folder 8)
    - Cyprus, 1965-1973 (Folder 9)
    - Czechoslovakia, 1969 (Folder 10)
    - Denmark, 1964-1977 (Folder 11)
    - Dominican Republic, 1971 (Folder 12)
    - Ecuador, 1957-1961 (Folder 13)
    - France
      - 1945-1967 (Folder 14)
      - 1969-1976 (Folder 15)
    - Germany, 1954-1978 (Folder 16)
    - Great Britain
      - 1955-1974 (Folder 17)
      - 1975-1979 (Folder 18)
    - Greece, 1957-1974 (Folder 19)
    - Guyana, 1962-1967 (Folder 20)
    - Hong Kong, 1969-1971 (Folder 21)
    - India, 1957-1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Indonesia, 1946-1967 (Folder 2)
    - Iran, 1966 (Folder 3)
    - Israel, 1960-1976 (Folder 4)
    - Italy, 1945-1973 (Folder 5)
    - Jamaica, 1961-1969 (Folder 6)
    - Japan, 1962-1975 (Folder 7)
    - Lebanon, 1970-1972 (Folder 8)
    - Luxemburg, 1972 (Folder 9)
    - Malaysia, 1967 (Folder 10)
    - Mexico
      - 1940-1969 (Folder 11)
      - 1970-1976 (Folder 12)
    - Mozambique, 1967 (Folder 13)
    - Netherlands, 1946-1976 (Folder 14)
    - New Zealand, 1965-1977 (Folder 15)
    - Nigeria, 1954-1970 (Folder 16)
    - Pakistan, 1971 (Folder 17)
    - Peru, 1957-1976 (Folder 18)
    - South Africa, 1957 (Folder 19)
    - Spain, 1967-1977 (Folder 20)
    - Sri Lanka, 1957-1976 (Folder 21)
    - Sweden, 1972-1978 (Folder 22)
    - Switzerland, 1957-1971 (Folder 23)
    - Tanzania, 1966-1969 (Folder 24)
    - Turkey, n.d. (Folder 25)
    - United States
      - 1927-1939 (Folder 26)
      - 1940-1942 (Folder 27)
      - 1943 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 1944-1948 (Folder 2)
      - 1950-1957 (Folder 3)
      - 1958-1961 (Folder 4)
      - 1962
        - January-February (Folder 5)
        - March (Folder 6)
        - April-September (Folder 7)
      - 1963-1967 (Folder 8)
      - 1968-1970 (Folder 9)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 1973-1975 (Folder 2)
      - 1976 (Folder 3)
      - 1977 (Folder 4)
      - 1978-1980 (Folder 5)
    - Uruguay, 1968-1972 (Folder 6)
    - Venezuela, 1970-1977 (Folder 7)
    - Vietnam, 1966 (Folder 8)
    - Yugoslavia, 1970 (Folder 9)
    - Zambia, 1964-1971 (Folder 10)
  - Abern, Martin
    - 1935-1936 (Folder 11)
    - 1937 (Folder 12)
  - Aguilar, Manuel and Mara (Mexico)
    - 1962-1968 (Folder 13)
    - 1969-1977 (Folder 14)
  - Alarco, Rosa (Peru), 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, Robert J., 1969-1977 (Folder 2)
  - Ali, Tariq (Pakistan; Great Britain), 1968-1973 (Folder 3)
  - Amador, Fausto (Nicaragua; Costa Rica), 1977-1978 (Folder 4)
  - Ames, Philip (U.S.; Mexico), 1970-1971 (Folder 5)
  - Anderson, Paul, 1937-1940 (Folder 6)
  - Archer, John and Mary (Great Britain), 1976 (Folder 7)
  - Aronson, James, 1960 (Folder 8)
  - Austin, John and Rudie, 1943-1972 (Folder 9)
  - Bagel, Bobbie, 1974-1976 (Folder 10)
  - Banerji, Sailen (India), 1971-1974 (Folder 11)
  - Barnes, Jack, 1965-1970 (Folder 12)
  - Beauvais, Jean-Pierre (France), 1971-1978 (Folder 13)
  - Belfrage, Cedric (Great Britain; U.S.; Mexico), 1966 (Folder 14)
  - Birney, Earle (Canada), 1937-1939 (Folder 15)
  - Blanco, Hugo (Peru)
    - 1969-1970 (Folder 16)
    - 1971-1973 (Folder 17)
  - Blick, Robin (Great Britain), 1975-1976 (Folder 18)
  - Bombaro, Natalie, 1975-1980 (Folder 19)
  - Bornstein, Sam (Great Britain), 1976 (Folder 20)
  - Boulton, James E., 1958-1962 (Folder 21)
  - Braverman, Harry, 1970 (Folder 22)
  - Breitman, George
    - 1943-1959 (Folder 23)
    - 1960-1971 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1972-1979 (Folder 2)
  - Broue, Pierre (France), 1972-1973 (Folder 3)
  - Brundy, Peggy, 1969-1970 (Folder 4)
  - Burch, Kay, 1943-1979 (Folder 5)
  - Cadart, Claude and Lily (France), 1966-1972 (Folder 6)
  - Camejo, Daniel (Venezuela; Mexico; U.S.)
    - 1961-1965 (Folder 7)
    - 1966 (Folder 8)
    - 1967-1973 (Folder 9)
  - Camejo, Maria (Venezuela; Mexico), 1962-1965 (Folder 10)
  - Camejo, Peter (Venezuela; U.S.), 1961-1972 (Folder 11)
  - Cannon, James P.
    - 1937-1952 (Folder 12)
    - 1953 (Folder 13)
    - 1954 (Folder 14)
    - 1955-1959 (Folder 15)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1965-1974 (Folder 2)
  - Carlson, Grace, 1951 (Folder 3)
  - Carvajal, R. (Cuba), 1961 (Folder 4)
  - Charlier, Fernand (France; Belgium), 1966 (Folder 5)
  - Chertov, Morris and Pearl, 1958-1976 (Folder 6)
  - Chester, Bob and Anne
    - 1944-1965 (Folder 7)
    - 1967-1972 (Folder 8)
    - 1973-1976 (Folder 9)
    - 1977-1979 (Folder 10)
  - Clarke, George, 1940-1948 (Folder 11)
  - Coates, Ken (Great Britain)
    - 1963-1975 (Folder 12)
    - 1976-1978 (Folder 13)
  - Cochran, Bert, 1940 (Folder 14)
  - Cookridge, E. H. (Great Britain), 1977 (Folder 15)
  - Coover, Oscar, Jr., and Rossa, Della, 1961-1976 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Coover, Oscar, Sr., 1939-1941 (Folder 2)
  - Cornell, Charles (U.S.; Mexico), 1940-1946 (Folder 3)
  - Cowley, Joyce, 1957 (Folder 4)
  - Cumming, Bill, 1957-1975 (Folder 5)
  - Curtiss, Charles and Lillian (U.S.; Mexico), 1940-1979 (Folder 6)
  - Desai, Magan (India), 1967-1976 (Folder 7)
  - Deutscher, Isaac and Tamara (Poland; Great Britain), 1960-1978 (Folder 8)
  - DeWolfe, Louise (sister of Joseph Hansen), 1947-1977 (Folder 9)
  - Di Giuliomaria, Sirio (Italy)
    - 1963-1968 (Folder 10)
    - 1969-1974 (Folder 11)
  - Dobbs, Farrell
    - 1943-1958 (Folder 12)
    - 1961 (Folder 13)
    - 1962 (Folder 14)
    - 1963
      - January-April (Folder 15)
      - May-December (Folder 16)
    - 1964
      - January-May (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - June-December (Folder 2)
    - 1965-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Dobbs, Marvel, 1958-1978 (Folder 4)
  - Dobbs, Sherry
    - 1956-1962 (Folder 5)
    - 1963-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Doritty, Barbara, 1964-1975 (Folder 7)
  - Dowson, Ross (Canada)
    - 1945-1962 (Folder 8)
    - 1963-1965 (Folder 9)
    - 1966-1968 (Folder 10)
    - 1969-1979 (Folder 11)
  - Draper, Hal, 1962 (Folder 12)
  - Dunayevskaya, Raya, 1938-1976 (Folder 13)
  - Dunne, Vincent R., 1951-1966 (Folder 14)
  - Edwards, Theodore, 1958-1970 (Folder 15)
  - Fair Play for Cuba Committee (U.S. and Canada; re Cuba), 1960-1967. See also Olson, Vernel (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Farrell, James T., 1939-1976 (Folder 2)
  - Feingold, Carl, 1958-1963 (Folder 3)
  - Fender, David (U.S.; Europe)
    - 1965-1966 (Folder 4)
    - 1967 (Folder 5)
    - 1968-1971 (Folder 6)
  - Ferguson, Duncan
    - 1944-1961 (Folder 7)
    - 1962-1974 (Folder 8)
  - Fernandez, Octavio, and family (Mexico), 1946-1962 (Folder 9)
  - Fischler, Harry, 1940 (Folder 10)
  - Foley, Gerry, n.d. (Folder 11)
  - Fourth International. International Committee, 1962 (Folder 12)
  - Fourth International. International Secretariat, 1953 (Folder 13)
  - Fourth International. Revolutionary Marxist Tendency, 1976 (Folder 14)
  - Fourth International. United Secretariat (includes letters written collectively to, or collectively by, Pierre Frank, Livio Maitan and Ernest Mandel)
    - 1966-1969 (Folder 15)
    - 1970-1978 (Folder 16)
  - Fox, Art, 1957-1958 (Folder 17)
  - France. Consulat (New York City), 1971 (Folder 18)
  - Frank, Pierre (France)
    - 1956-1966 (Folder 19)
    - 1967-1968 (Folder 20)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1976 (Folder 2)
  - Frankel, Jan (Czechoslovakia; U.S.), 1939 (Folder 3)
  - Fraser, Richard, 1957 (Folder 4)
  - Fryer, Peter (Great Britain), 1957 (Folder 5)
  - Galindez, Ricardo (Venezuela), 1976-1977 (Folder 6)
  - Garrett, Jan, 1966-1972 (Folder 7)
  - Garza, Richard (U.S.; Mexico), 1957-1971 (Folder 8)
  - Geldman, Max, 1953 (Folder 9)
  - Geller, Jules, 1940-1952 (Folder 10)
  - Genecin, Milton and Tybie, 1955-1980 (Folder 11)
  - Gibbs, Wendell, 1928 (Folder 12)
  - Glass, C. Frank and Grace (South Africa; U.S.; re China and Philippines)
    - 1954-1958 (Folder 13)
    - 1959-1967 (Folder 14)
    - 1968-1970 (Folder 15)
    - 1971-1973 (Folder 16)
    - 1974-1976 (Folder 17)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Glenn, John R. (Canada; Philippines), 1969-1972 (Folder 2)
  - Godchau, Jean-Francois (France), 1969-1978 (Folder 3)
  - Goldman, Albert, 1939-1949 (Folder 4)
  - Gordon, Sam (U.S.; Great Britain)
    - 1962-1963 (Folder 5)
    - 1964-1968 (Folder 6)
    - 1969-1975 (Folder 7)
    - 1976-1979 (Folder 8)
  - Grant, Ted (Great Britain), 1963 (Folder 9)
  - Gregorich, Barbara, 1967-1970 (Folder 10)
  - Halstead, Fred and Virginia, 1958-1977 (Folder 11)
  - Hanman, Bert, 1935-1939 (Folder 12)
  - Hansen, Allan (brother of Joseph Hansen)
    - 1937-1942 (Folder 13)
    - 1943 (Folder 14)
    - 1944-1952 (Folder 15)
    - 1953-1963 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Hansen, Beatrice (sister-in-law of Joseph Hansen)
    - 1947-1956 (Folder 2)
    - 1957 (Folder 3)
    - 1958-1961 (Folder 4)
    - 1962 (Folder 5)
    - 1963-1966 (Folder 6)
    - 1967
      - February-April (Folder 7)